Inventory of the Milo E. Rowell papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Milo E. Rowell papers
1945-1975
1945-1946
75050
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box (0.2 linear feet)
Reports, drafts, and memoranda relating to the writing of the revised Japanese constitution. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Rowell, Milo E.
MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.
Whitney, Courtney.
Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers. Government Section.
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
Lieutenant colonel, United States Army; military lawyer, Government Section, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, 1945-1946.
Scope and Content of Collection
Reports, drafts, and memoranda relating to the writing of the revised Japanese constitution.
United States. Army.; Constitutional history--Japan.; Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.
- Memo, 1975 June 16 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Written by Milo E. Rowell as an explanatory introduction to the collection, relaying the context of the documents and their significance. Individual introductory notes by Rowell also appear within many of the folders.
- Draft Japanese constitution proposal submitted by the Constitution Investigating Society, 1945 December 27 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Documents related to draft Japanese constitution proposal, 1945 December 12-31 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  Includes press translations of the draft Japanese constitution proposal and ensuing discussions, and a rough draft of the Japanese constitution from December 12, 1945, with annotations.
- Original draft of proposed Constitution of Japan, one of five numbered copies, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- "Report of Government Section to Far Eastern Commission,", 1946 January 17 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Drafts and memos 1-29, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 6-9)
- "Gist of the Revision of the Constitution,", undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
- Meetings of the Steering Committee, 1946 February 6-9 (Box-folder 1: 11)
- Declassified U.S. government records, 1946 (Reading room workstation)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover. Available as searchable PDF files.
  - 2017 release of records, 1946
    Certain documents numbered by Rowell; the remainder can be found in Box 1, Folders 6-9.
    - "Comments on the Document 'Gist of the Revision to the Constitution',", 1946 February?
    - 6. Check sheet, Government Section (General Courtney Whitney) to Commander-in-Chief, "Constitutional Revision,", 1946 February 6
    - 7. Ellerman report of Government Section meeting, 1946 February 4
    - 8. "Three Basic Points Stated by Supreme Commander to be 'Musts' in Constitutional Revision," Government Section paper, circa 1946 February 4
    - 10. "Draft of Preamble and Article I," original drafts of committee reports, 1946?
    - 11. Ellerman notes on minutes of Government Section, Public Administration Division meetings, 1946 February 5-12
    - 12. Check sheet, Government Section (General Courtney Whitney) to Commander-in-Chief, "Constitutional Revision,", 1946 February 10
      Cover sheet includes the following note (by Rowell?): "This draft was modified by the elimination of a portion of the Civil Rights Article as suggested by General MacArthur to General Whitney on 11 February 1946."
    - 14. Check sheet, Government Section (General Courtney Whitney) to Commander-in-Chief, "Constitutional Revision,", 1946 February 10
      Cover sheet includes the following note (by Rowell?): "I have no copy of this draft. There was one section in Bill of Rights that was questioned by General McArthur when he discussed this with General Whitney. When General Whitney in turn discussed this with me and then the Steering Committee as a whole, we concurred that such section should be eliminated, rewrote that portion and resubmitted the draft to General MacArthur on 11 February, which he then approved. So far as I know, all copies of this draft were destroyed."
    - 16. Memorandum to Chief, Government Section, discussing outline of Matsumoto draft, 1946 February 12
    - 21. Letter from Dr. G. Matsumoto to General Courtney Whitney enclosing "Supplementary Explanation Concerning the Constitutional Revision,", 1946 February 18
    - 22. Memorandum from General Courtney Whitney to the Supreme Commander regarding visit from Mr. Jiro Shirasu and the Japanese Cabinet's request for an extension to accept the principles of the constitutional draft, 1946 February 19
      Also includes a memorandum dated 18 February 1946 with the subject "'Supplementary Explanation of Proposed Constitution Revision' Presented by Mr. Shirasu," and referencing the above letter from Dr. Matsumoto.
    - 26. Memorandum from Charles L. Kades and Alfred R. Hussey to the Chief, Government Section, regarding a picnic at the estate of Mr. Wataru Narahashi, Chief Secretary of the Cabinet, and discussions there about the constitution, 1946 February 25